San José de Queréndaro Hacienda Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
San José de Queréndaro Hacienda Records 1543-1922 1580-1883
MSS84054
2 items
2 containers
0.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Bound volumes of files kept by the Jesuits, original owners of the hacienda. Subjects include the acquisition and sale of land, ownership disputes, water rights, rental of property, agricultural production, livestock and livestock brands, and relations with the Indigenous people of Mexico. Also includes correspondence and fiscal accounts with the local railroad company.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abad y Queipo, Manuel, 1751-1825.; Bárcena, Juan.; Bárcena, Miguel.; Heras Soto, Ignacio de.; Heras Soto, Mariana de, 1791-; Heras Soto, Mariana de, 1809-; Heras Soto, Sebastian de, conde de Heras Soto, 1746-1814 or 1815.; López Pimentel, Tomás.; Peña, José Antonio López.; Pimentel y Heras, José.
Organizations
Catholic Church--Mexico.; Colegio de Valladolid (Mexico); Jesuits--Mexico.
Subjects
Agriculture--Mexico.; Haciendas--Mexico.; Indians of Mexico.; Inheritance and succession--Mexico.; Land tenure--Mexico.; Law--Mexico.; Livestock brands--Mexico.; Livestock--Mexico.; Loans--Mexico.; Manufacturing industries--Mexico.; Mortgages--Mexico.; Railroads--Mexico.; Real property--Mexico.; Rent--Mexico.; Right of property--Mexico.; Water rights--Mexico.; Women--Mexico.
Places
Mexico--History--Spanish colony, 1540-1810.; Mexico--History--Wars of Independence, 1810-1821.; Michoacán de Ocampo (Mexico)--History.; San José de Queréndaro Hacienda (Mexico)
Acquisition Information
The records of the San José de Queréndaro Hacienda were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1997.
Related Material
The documents are linked to records of the Santa Clara de Tulillo Hacienda also in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the San José de Queréndaro Hacienda are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the San José de Queréndaro Hacienda consist of two manuscript volumes relating principally to the areas surrounding La Laguna de Cuitzeo, Michoacán de Ocampo, in the period 1543-1922. Written in Spanish, the bulk of the documents span the years 1580-1883, with the years 1700-1731, 1805-1839, and 1862-1883 especially well covered. Each volume is separated into cuadernos, subdivisions based on subject content.
The Compañía de Jesús (Society of Jesus) received official royal title to the lands in 1643. As early as 1631 the Hacienda de Queréndaro, under the jurisdiction of the Colegio de Valladolid, produced 1000 bushels of wheat, 600 bushels of maize, and raised 200 cattle and 30 horses. The Jesuit occupiers of the land added to their holdings, most notably entering into an agreement in 1720 to purchase the adjoining haciendas of San Antonio, San Bernardo, Zinzimeo, and la Trasquila from the Conde de Lizarraga. By 1767 production included wheat, maize, chiles, beans, sugar, and both large and small livestock. In 1767 the expulsion of the Jesuits from all Spanish territory as enemies of the Crown resulted in the expropriation of Queréndaro by the Ramo de Temporalidades.
In 1804 the Condes de Heras Soto purchased the estate from the Crown. Sebastian de Heras Soto served as a royalist commander in the War of Independence. His son, Manuel de Heras Soto, signed the Act of Mexican Independence, and his decendant, Tómas López Pimentel, was a supporter of the Mexican empire of Maximillian of Hapsburg. During the nineteenth century, the Heras/Pimentel family were accused of claiming or purchasing lands which ostensibly belonged to the neighboring indigenous towns of Zinapécuaro and Queréndaro.
Documents in these volumes served as supporting evidence in disputes between the owners of the Hacienda de Queréndaro, neighboring estates, and nearby indigenous pueblos. The majority of the litigation revolved around the claims of the Jesuits and subsequent owners of the Hacienda de Queréndaro to various lands and waters in the region. These claims were frequently disputed by the Hacienda de Santa Clara de Tulillo and the Pueblos de Queréndaro and Zinapécuaro.
The records include various Real Provisiones (royal decrees), Audiencia rulings, mercedes (land grants), acts of land possession, various suits and countersuits, correspondence, estate inventories, wills and testaments, bills of sale, rental agreements, mortgage/loan material, and fiscal accounts. Subjects include the acquisition and sale of land, ownership disputes, water rights, the establishment of property boundaries, rental of property, relations with indigenous villages, legal procedure, the role of women in estate operations, inheritance, Temporalidades (the royal branch responsible for the sale of Jesuit properties), the impact of the Mexican War of Independence, agricultural production, the functioning of an obraje, and railway construction. The documents may have been assembled in their present form in the 1920s-1930s as part of the last recorded dispute between the Hacienda de Queréndaro and Ferrocarriles Nacionales de México y Anexas.
Individual owners and important figures appearing in the text include Manuel Abad y Quiepo, Juan Bárcena, Miguel Bárcena, Sebastian de Heras Soto, first Conde de Heras Soto, Ignacio de Heras Soto, Mariana de Heras Soto (b. 1791), Mariana de Heras Soto (b.1809), Tomás López Pimentel, José Antonio López Peña, and José Pimentel y Heras.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged into two volumes, each separated into cuadernos and subdivided based on subject content.
Container List
- Volume 1 (Box 1, Cuaderno 1-3)
  - 1676-1700 (Box 1, Cuaderno 1-3)
    - Documents submitted as testimony in a suit by Joachin de Cuevas to collect purchase amount from Don Francisco de Arteta Verganza for the sale of the haciendas of La Trasquila, San Bernardo, Sinzimeo, Chapitiro, and San Antonio (Box 1, Cuaderno 1-3)
    - Documents relating to an earlier agreement to sell these lands ultimately declared null and void; includes complete inventory of estate (Box 1, Cuaderno 1-3)
    - Testimony relating to the determination of boundaries with neighboring estates; includes measurements and testimony of witnesses (Box 1, Cuaderno 1-3)
  - 1700 (Box 1, Cuaderno 4)
    - Account of the inspection of the obraje of the Jesuit Hacienda de Queréndaro, property of the Colegio de Valladolid 5 (Box 1, Cuaderno 4)
  - 1591-1701 (Box 1, Cuaderno 5)
    - Copy of royal decrees ordering that all lands held without legal title must seek a composición de tierras (Box 1, Cuaderno 5)
    - Copy of document granting of composiciones to all Jesuit estates in New Spain; includes descriptions of the properties of the Colegios of San Pedro y San Pablo, Santa Anna, Spiritu Santo de la Puebla, San Ylefonso de la Puebla, Tepotzlan, Oaxaca, and Valladolid (including Hacienda de Queréndaro) 6 (Box 1, Cuaderno 5)
  - 1701-1702 (Box 1, Cuaderno 6)
    - Proceedings in suits by the Jesuit Colegio de Valladolid disputing ownership of Francisco de Arteta 7 (Box 1, Cuaderno 6)
  - 1640-1703 (Box 1, Cuaderno 7)
    - Land title, sale transactions, and posesiones de tierras presented by Bartolomé González de Rebolledo as supporting evidence in his claim of legal title to two caballerías de tierra in "el mal pais” (Box 1, Cuaderno 7)
  - 1703 (Box 1, Cuaderno 8)
    - Power of attorney given by the Colegio de Valladolid to Antonio Guardado (Box 1, Cuaderno 8)
    - Sale of twenty-three sitios de ganado menor by Collegio de Valladolid to Doña Juana de Luna Yazellano, Mariscala de Castilla (Box 1, Cuaderno 8)
  - 1582-1705 (Box 1, Cuaderno 9-10)
    - Proceedings in a suit filed by Conde del Fresno and Don José Marín y Villaseñor against the Colegio de Valladolid over ownership of various properties, including two caballerías near the Pueblo of Queréndaro, and the haciendas of San Bernardo, Sinsimeo, and Tepetongo; includes land grants, and testimony of witnesses (Box 1, Cuaderno 9-10)
  - 1707 (Box 1, Cuaderno 11)
    - Cancellation of a mortgage agreement originally granted by the Colegio de Valladolid to the Monjas del Rosario de Zinapécuaro (Box 1, Cuaderno 11)
  - 1707 (Box 1, Cuaderno 12)
    - Petition submitted by Conde del Fresno demanding the return of the Hacienda de Sinsimeo which the Jesuits had sold (Box 1, Cuaderno 12)
  - 1655-1709 (Box 1, Cuaderno 13-14)
    - Suit pursued by the Colegio de Valladolid on behalf of ‟los Naturales de Indaparapeo” seeking the restoration of the Hacienda de Tepetongo to the naturales (Box 1, Cuaderno 13-14)
    - Countersuit filed by José Marín y Villaseñor against the Colegio de Valladolid for illegal intrusion on the Hacienda de Tepetongo (Box 1, Cuaderno 13-14)
    - Inventory of the estate of Juan de la Rea which included disputed lands (Box 1, Cuaderno 13-14)
  - 1710 (Box 1, Cuaderno 15)
    - Resolution of a dispute over various lands in favor of the Colegio de Valladolid which it had pursued against Doña Leonor de Sámano y Sesati and Francisco Gonzalez (Box 1, Cuaderno 15)
  - 1543-1718 (Box 1, Cuaderno 16-19)
    - Proceedings and material presented as testimony in an appeal/continuation of the suit which appeared as resolved in Cuaderno 15; documents include material related to the sale of the haciendas of Sinsimeo, San Bernardo, and La Trasquila de San Antonio (sold by Francisco de Arteta to Don Joseph Ventura de Elexalde); financing records, posesiones de tierras, and various sixteenth and seventeenth century land grants; 1718 royal decree concerning the restoration of these lands to the Jesuits (Box 1, Cuaderno 16-19)
  - 1718 (Box 1, Cuaderno 20)
    - Proceedings in a boundary dispute between the Hacienda de Queréndaro and the Hacienda de los Naranjos (Box 1, Cuaderno 20)
  - 1720 (Box 1, Cuaderno 21)
    - Transaction of sale of lands contained in the Hacienda de Chapitiro between Conde de Lizarraga (son of Don Joseph Ventura de Arizaga y Elexalde) and the Colegio de Valladolid (Box 1, Cuaderno 21)
  - circa 1780-1800, undated (Box 1, Cuaderno 22)
    - Miscellaneous documents regarding an unresolved dispute between the haciendas of Queréndaro and Santa Clara over access to the Rio de Parras (Box 1, Cuaderno 22)
  - 1716 (Box 1, Cuaderno 23)
    - Royal decree granting the Colegio de Valladolid ownership of lands disputed by the colegio and the Pueblo de Queréndaro (Box 1, Cuaderno 23)
  - 1724 (Box 1, Cuaderno 24)
    - Rental agreement authorized by Conde de Lizarraga for Don José de Bárcena and Don Pedro de Ibarra (Box 1, Cuaderno 24)
  - 1725 (Box 1, Cuaderno 25)
    - Documents regarding the sale of lands by Conde de Lizarraga to the Colegio de Valladolid See same container, Cuaderno 21; lands include the haciendas of San Antonio, San Bernardo, Sinsimeo, and La Trasquila (Box 1, Cuaderno 25)
  - 1727 (Box 1, Cuaderno 26)
    - Material related to the donation of twenty-five sitios de ganado menor in "El Reino de León " by Gertrudis de Aguilar to the Colegio de Valladolid (Box 1, Cuaderno 26)
  - 1727-1730 (Box 1, Cuaderno 27-28)
    - Royal decrees regarding the Hacienda de Queréndaro's relations with neighboring estates; subjects include the prevention of damage caused to Queréndaro's crops by unrestrained cattle and the prohibition on hiring of former Queréndaro workers (Box 1, Cuaderno 27-28)
  - 1589-1731 (Box 1, Cuaderno 29-32)
    - Proceedings and testimony in a suit filed by Conde de Lizarraga seeking nullification of the sale to the Colegio de Valladolid of those lands identified in Cuadernos 21 and 25 (Box 1, Cuaderno 29-32)
  - 1591-1732 (Box 1, Cuaderno 33)
    - 1732 copies of titles and land grants pertaining to the land contained within the haciendas of Cupantaro and San Bartolome (Box 1, Cuaderno 33)
  - 1592-1732 (Box 1, Cuaderno 34-35)
    - Documents regarding the Colegio de Valladolid’s claim to lands on La Ysla de San Miguel Sirio (Box 1, Cuaderno 34-35)
  - 1601-1733 (Box 1, Cuaderno 36)
    - Proceedings in the nullification suit pursued by Conde de Lizarraga in the matter of the sale of land to the Colegio de Valladolid (Box 1, Cuaderno 36)
    - Land title documents for La Ysla de San Miguel Sirio (Box 1, Cuaderno 36)
- Volume 2 (Box 2, Cuaderno 11)
  - 1807-1809 (Box 2, Cuaderno 11)
    - Proceedings in a suit between Don Sebastián de Heras Soto, owner of Hacienda de Queréndaro, and Don Sebastián de Odriosola, owner of Hacienda de La Bartolilla, over ownership of the waters of the Ojo Caliente (Box 2, Cuaderno 11)
  - 1811 (Box 2, Cuaderno 12)
    - Letter from Comandante del batallón de patriotas Don Sebastian de Heras Soto claiming damages done to the Hacienda de Queréndaro by insurgent forces and request for reparations (Box 2, Cuaderno 12)
  - 1805-1806 (Box 2, Cuaderno 13)
    - Proceedings in a suit between the Hacienda de Santa Clara and the Hacienda de Queréndaro over access to the water of La Sanja Prieta (Box 2, Cuaderno 13)
  - 1805-1824 (Box 2, Cuaderno 14)
    - Petition for protection of land owned by Sebastián de Heras Soto, including the Hacienda de Queréndaro and Antonia de Heras in 1837 (Box 2, Cuaderno 14)
    - 1824 copy of acts of 1805-1806 concerning possession of the Hacienda de Queréndaro (Box 2, Cuaderno 14)
  - 1805-1839 (Box 2, Cuaderno 15)
    - Copies of proceedings in a suit between Sebastián de Heras Soto and Sebastián de Odriosola See also same container, Cuaderno11 (Box 2, Cuaderno 15)
  - 1837-1839 (Box 2, Cuaderno 16)
    - Testimony concerning the division of the estate of Manuel de Heras Soto between Mariana and Antonia de Heras in 1837 (Box 2, Cuaderno 16)
  - 1662-1871 (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Proceedings in a suit to nullify a sale (1727-1806) originally between Conde de Lizarraga and Colegio de Valladolid, continued by Ramón de Goicochea and Sebastián de Heras Soto, owners of Hacienda de Queréndaro, and José Antonio López Peña, owner of Hacienda de Santa Clara See also Container 1, Cuadernos 29-32 and 36 (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Last will and testament of Gregorio Gonzalez de Rebolledo (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Contract beginning and concluding a partnership between Sebastián de Heras Soto and Juan Antonio Aguilera for the administration of the Hacienda de Queréndaro (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Last will and testament of Don Francisco de Arteta y Verganza (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Titles of ownership of the Hacienda de Queréndaro from Ramón de Goicochea (1782) to Mariana Heras de Pimentel (1839) (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Possession of the Hacienda de Queréndaro by Ramón de Goicochea (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
    - Map of tenant-cultivated lands in El Potrero La Quemada (1871) (Box 2, Cuaderno 17)
  - 1821-1862 (Box 2, Cuaderno 18)
    - Proceedings in suit to nullify the sale continued by Manuel de Heras Soto, second Conde de Heras Soto, and José Pimentel, owners of Hacienda de Queréndaro See also same container, Cuaderno 17, and Container 1, Cuadernos 29-32 and 36 (Box 2, Cuaderno 18)
  - 1846-1864 (Box 2, Cuaderno 19)
    - Division of estate of Manuel de Heras Soto (Box 2, Cuaderno 19)
    - Purchase of various lands from the Pueblo de Queréndaro by Don Tomás López Pimentel (Box 2, Cuaderno 19)
  - 1830-1864 (Box 2, Cuaderno 20)
    - Copies of documents pertaining to the division of the estate of Don Sebastián de Heras Soto (Box 2, Cuaderno 20)
  - 1839-1883 (Box 2, Cuaderno 21)
    - Power of attorney given by Tomás López Pimentel to José Pimentel y Heras to manage the affairs of his estate, including the Hacienda de Queréndaro Documents pertaining to the purchase of land in El Potrero Grande by José Pimentel y Heras from members of the Pueblo de Queréndaro (Box 2, Cuaderno 21)
  - 1882-1922 (Box 2, Cuaderno 22)
    - Arrangements between José Pimentel y Heras and La Compañia Constructora Nacional Mexicana to donate land for the passage of the railway through the Hacienda de Queréndaro (Box 2, Cuaderno 22)
    - 1922 correspondence between Carlos Haghenbeck, the last recorded owner of the Hacienda de Queréndaro, and Ferrocarrilles Nacionales de México y Anexos relating to a dispute over the hacienda’s access to the railway (Box 2, Cuaderno 22)